

- Machine learning specialist
- Computer vision specialist
- Programmer

Ricardo Cruz

Valongo, Portugal+351 934741617

ricardo.pdm.cruz@gmail.com

A http://rpmcruz.github.io

For the last few years, I have been working at INESC TEC – an institute that does both academic research and industry development. I have been doing both machine learning and computer vision, working in TensorFlow, PyTorch, and OpenCV.

I have just completed my Ph.D. in Computer Science (june 2021). During the Ph.D., I have been serving a few hours per week as a Teacher Assistant at the Faculty of Engineering, University of Porto, helping teach Python and C++. In 2021, I was awarded the Pedagogy Award based on student feedback.

SKILLS: Python \cdot C \cdot C++ \cdot Java \cdot R \cdot MATLAB \cdot TensorFlow \cdot PyTorch \cdot OpenCV \cdot SQL \cdot Git

WORK EXPERIENCE

Oct. 2015–Jul. 2021 | INESC TEC

Machine Learning Specialist

INESC TEC is an R&D institute whose headquarters are located in Porto. I collaborated in the following projects:

2020-2021 CadPath.AI: high-performing computing plataform in collaboration with IMP for molecular diagnosis of cancer cells

2018–2020 CLARE: low-cost mobile device for cervical cancer diagnosis in collaboration with Fraunhofer

2015–2017 NanoSTIMA: medical machine learning systems, in collaboration with CINTESIS, FMUP and IBMC

– Internal awards

- 2021 march: outstanding recognition award

https://bip.inesctec.pt/en/especiaisdecorrida/

ricardo-cruz-ctm-2/

- 2018 sept: outstanding recognition award http://bip-archive.inesctec.pt/en/196/fora-de-serie.html

Sept. 2018–Aug. 2021 | FEUP

Teacher Assistant (part-time)

- Teaching Python (EIC0005) and C/C++ (EIC0012) for MIEIC

- 2021: received FEUP pedagogic award, voted by students

Mar.–Jul. 2015 | Flykt Startup

I was involved in a non-successful startup whose goal was to search for travel destinations. I was involved in the NLP part.

EDUCATION

 $\mathbf{2016}\text{--}\mathbf{2021}\mid \mathsf{Ph.D.}$ in Computer Science

University of Porto, Minho and Aveiro (joint degree)

- Thesis title: Re-thinking a Deep Learning Pipeline for Images

- Supervisors: Jaime S. Cardoso and Joaquim F. Pinto Costa

- - 12 publications, 1 best paper award

2014–2015 | MSc in Mathematical Engineering

Faculty of Sciences, University of Porto

- Graduated with honors: 18 out of 20 points

 $\mathbf{2009}\text{--}\mathbf{2012}$ | BSc in Computer Science

Faculty of Sciences, University of Porto

- Graduated with honors: 16 out of 20 points

Last update: July 13, 2021 Page 1 of 3

Work Experience (cont'd)

Sept. 2014–Feb. 2015 | Research Grant

Mathematics Center of the University of Porto

Research on epidemiological models: from differential equations to stochastic simulations and cellular automata.

Some of my Workshops

May 2021 | IEEE Bioengeering Society (EMBS - ISEL) Scikit-image and scikit-learn

Oct 2019 | DSPT Day

Lightning talk on class imbalance

August 2018 | Universidade Junior

"Escondidos nos Dados:" Teaching data science to highschool students

August 2018 | Porto Codes Meetups Building a Neural Network

Sept 2017 | Porto Codes Meetups Julia Programming Language

June 2017 | Python Meetup NumPy and Scikit-Learn

Oct 2016 | FEUP Code Week Python for scientific computing

SELECTED OPEN-SOURCE PORTFOLIO

2017 | Avito NLP competition @ Kaggle

Bronze award for results and silver award for engagement

2010 | Apoo, a virtual machine



I helped with the development of Apoo (together with Profs Rogério Reis and Nelma Moreira), a virtual machine that is currently being used to teach Assembly. Apoo is written in Python and GTK+.

2009 | EatFeed

RSS/Atom reader written in C++ and GTK+

https://github.com/rpmcruz/eatfeed



2006 and 2007 | Google Summer of Code

- 2007: LibreOffice dynamic layouts (C++)

- 2006: YaST port from GTK+ to Qt (C++)

2005 | J2ME and Android games

https://github.com/rpmcruz/android-games

Games written in Java Mobile Edition; more recently, I ported a couple of them to Android.

2005 | SuperTux, co-author

https://www.supertux.org/



While in high-school, I was part of the initial team developing this game. It is written in C++, SDL, and OpenGL.

- ► Find more of my open-source code at https://github.com/rpmcruz.
- ► Videos showing some of my work: https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCLS60CVgk_qPohhUqSPvLJw.

Last update: July 13, 2021 Page 2 of 3

Publications (indexed)

- 2021: Ordinal Losses for Classification of Cervical Cancer Risk
 T. Albuquerque, R. Cruz, J. Cardoso. Peer J Computer Science [IF: 3.09]
- 2021: Background Invariance by Adversarial Learning
 R. Cruz, R. Prates, E. Filho, J. Costa, J. Cardoso. 25th International Conference on Pattern Recognition (ICPR), IEEE [CAPES: A2]
- 3. **2019:** Automatic Augmentation by Hill Climbing R. Cruz, J. Costa, J. Cardoso. 28th International Conference on Artificial Neural Networks (ICANN), Springer [CAPES: B1]
- 4. **2019:** Averse Deep Semantic Segmentation R. Cruz, J. Costa, J. Cardoso. 41st Engineering in Medicine and Biology Conference (EMBC), IEEE [CAPES: A2]
- 5. **2019:** Insulator visual non-conformity detection in overhead power distribution lines using deep learning R. Prates, R. Cruz, A. Marotta, R. Ramos, E. Filho, J. Cardoso. Journal Computers & Electrical Engineering, Springer [IF: 2.66]
- 2018: A Class Imbalance Ordinal Method for Alzheimer's Disease Classification
 R. Cruz, M. Silveira, J. Cardoso. 2018 International Workshop on Pattern Recognition in Neuroimaging (PRNI), IEEE
- 2018: Binary ranking for ordinal class imbalance
 R. Cruz, K. Fernandes, J. Costa, M. Pérez Ortiz, J. Cardoso. Journal Pattern Analysis and Applications,
 Springer [IF: 1.51]
- 8. **2018:** Deep image segmentation by quality inference K. Fernandes, R. Cruz, J. Cardoso. International Joint Conference on Neural Networks (IJCNN), IEEE [CAPES: A2]
- 9. **2017:** Constraining type II error: building intentionally biased classifiers R. Cruz, K. Fernandes, J. Costa, J. Cardoso. International Work-conference on Artificial Neural Networks (IWANN), Springer [CAPES: B1]
- 10. **2017:** Fine-to-coarse ranking in ordinal and imbalanced domains: an application to liver transplantation M. Pérez-Ortiz, K. Fernandes, R. Cruz, J. Cardoso. International Work-conference on Artificial Neural Networks (IWANN), Springer [CAPES: B1]
- 11. **2017**: Combining ranking with traditional methods for ordinal class imbalance R. Cruz, K. Fernandes, J. Costa, M. Pérez-Ortiz, J. Cardoso. International Work-conference on Artificial Neural Networks (IWANN), Springer [CAPES: B1]
- 12. **2017**: Ordinal class imbalance with ranking R. Cruz, K. Fernandes, J. Costa, M. Pérez-Ortiz, J. Cardoso. Iberian conference on pattern recognition and image analysis (Ibpria), Springer [CAPES: B2]
- 13. **2016:** Tackling class imbalance with ranking R. Cruz, K. Fernandes, J. Costa, J. Cardoso. International Joint Conference on Neural Networks (IJCNN), IEEE [CAPES: A2]

Last update: July 13, 2021 Page 3 of 3